And second is the administrator of the office and here you're just in time for the O's.
The O's and just swear.
I state your name.
Exactly.
Okay.
I will say it then you guys repeat after me.
I accept that we'll say you name.
I.
To make room.
To.
I.
I will support obey in the fan constitution the United States.
And the constitution at the state of Oklahoma.
The constitution of the state of Oklahoma.
And that I will not knowing.
And that I will not knowingly.
Receive directly or indirectly.
And many or other valuable things.
any money or other valuable funding for the performance or non-performance for the performance or non-performance
any act or duty for please my office or the act or duty for paying to my office other than the compensation
amount by law other than the compensation allowed by law I further
further further swear or a firm that I will face faithfully discharge and I will take the late
discharge according to the best my ability according to the best of my building the duties of my office
during such time as I am a member the duties of my office I am a member of the city's
building and planning commission of the city of my office
Thank you.
Sign.
Do you have a license?
Yes.
That remains to be said.
Thank you.
For the purposes of this meeting, we just want to make sure everybody knows that I've
asked one of the members of the city's zoning and planning commission is on the speaker phone.
So be sure and speak up and then also if you speak, say your name and your address so
that he understands he can understand who you are and what's going on during the meeting.
Number three, there's election of a vice chairperson.
You have any thoughts?
Any person say, oh go off.
Okay.
Tim, you ready?
Sure.
I'll make a motion to make a motion to make a motion to make a motion to make a motion.
I'll certainly do.
Kim Rue?
Aye.
Reynolds?
Wester?
5.
Comber?
And over.
5.
Okay.
Number four is to prove the minutes from April the second, 2020.
Do we have any questions on this?
Do I have a motion to approve the minutes?
I'll second.
Um, Reynolds?
Uh.
Ingram?
All right.
Western?
I.
Kimberum.
And over.
Okay.
Number five is to public hearing concern and annexation and zoning of the below property to residential
multi-final family contingent on receipt of funding through local home before the housing
tax credit.
As everyone gone here and viewed the, uh, the application.
This is a, this is a public hearing time.
And if you have any comments or questions.
We're going to be here.
Yeah.
There you go.
We're actually going to have, we're going to do a presentation on that.
And we can do that now during the public hearing, so that you'll have an idea of what
is what we're talking about.
And it's kind of here in this county.
And we're going to have a better case for you.
I'm going to have to talk to you.
So.
This is for you.
Abescent project.
Waltz project.
This was done in 2002.
This is anyways the states.
And the new project that they're proposing in fact would be located behind this.
I went out this morning.
actually relocated behind us, I went out this morning because I just wanted to check on it.
And I'm behind the target piece to go on with Zoom.
Yes, sir.
Yeah.
This first picture right here is taken on Elm looking at these after part of the development.
So these were just a couple of shots to give you an idea of what's currently there.
This is a 24-minute apartment.
Complex.
You can see that it's number one and number two.
And then there's number three.
And then they have a little...
playground area. So, it's kind of far back there. I mean, that road's not very well-traveled
and some people don't even realize this about this is back there in this area. But before
we started, I wanted to kind of give me an idea of the work that they've done before. And, like
said, this was done in 2002. Right? Right, you don't know. Good evening. I'm Brett and
Lisa with Brett with Development. I have, if you don't have a packet of this presentation,
I haven't actually talked to you. That's not brochures by me. I'm going to kind of get
to just a few copies of the presentation. I have some brochures. Just kind of give it an overview
of our company. It's got some more pictures in there. And I also have some larger voters in case
you want to see some of the relevant elements. Just a quick little background about us. The
present I read with Development is with Ralph X-Roger. The shorter family has been in
affordable housing for 40 plus years. Kind of one of the things that is unique about us compared
to other developers is we are the developer, owner, general contractor and management company, we're
all in one. So, we're not going to build a property and then turn it over to separate management
company and walk away. So, as you can see from the photos of our property here in Miami, we take
great pride in what we do. We want to build a really good product. Something that the community
is going to be really proud of. That property is built in 2002. It looks virtually, probably pretty
similar to what it looked like the day that it was built. So, that's what you're going to get
whenever when you partner with us on doing a development. And we don't just do this. With our affordable
development, we do this for some of our conventional properties too. We're based out of job
in Missouri. We have a very large portfolio around the Dalton area, job in the Web City
Coral Junction. We operate in three different states over home, Missouri and Kansas. So, this
development specifically, I'll just kind of hit some highlights. Most of you already have the
package. So, this is basically just going to be a, it's not a second piece because it's actually
going to have a different name, but it will be next to the existing property. It's a single
story, family, occupant, project. It's going to be 32 units. Those will be 1 and 3 bedroom units.
They'll be 4, 1 bedroom units, 28, 3 bedroom units. And if you're kind of wondering why didn't you
pick any 2 bedroom units. We actually reached out to the public housing authority and see just
see what the need was, specifically for your community, for housing and what which units had a long
So they advised us, there's great need for one and three headphones, so that's why we chose that.
There's a rent over view on here.
There will be specific units targeted toward different airing meetings in comes.
Some of the amenities will include, there will be another community playground,
in addition to the one that's already there.
There will be on this new site.
So for the residents that are looking on that property,
there will be a community building.
It will primarily be an F-rated storage shelter,
large enough to accommodate everyone that lives within the development.
Let's see.
We'll have restaurants in the community building.
There will be computer work sessions within an access to large gathering area
for communal events, such as publics and get together.
This property is currently out of the city limits,
so we're requesting to annex the property in,
so that we can connect to the utilities that are available.
Just to the south and east of this property,
I just want to give to us to your city staff who've been very helpful in helping us prepare this application
and look at the utilities in order to make sure that we have our cost covered for this project.
So this property is 5.14 acres,
and you're requesting to donate from agriculture to our environmental families.
So that's kind of the first page.
And then...
Just throw that.
But can you go before you leave that first page?
I'm sorry.
I think you have the target rental by for your units.
Yep.
There will be 18 units targeting 60% area in the evening income,
and 14 units will be targeting 50% area in the evening income level.
So that's honestly one of the point criteria for the Oklahoma Housing Finance Agency.
They like to see us target the lowest possible income levels
to make sure that we're capturing everybody who needs housing,
so not everyone is just doing the right up the max level.
So it helps those lower income tenants.
Which, I believe that equates to about 400.
What is it about being in it for the 1.
So the 1.15% units are 4.20.
And the 60% units will be fought for 50.
And for the 3.15% units will be 600.
And the 60% units will be 6.8.
Anybody have any questions on the first page?
Access.
Okay, sure.
The next page is just kind of a couple of the overview.
I'd probably kind of already went over that.
We just list the part of the other way out of the page.
I'm kind of partnered with this.
in the past, when it's during the states.
The next page is the Minimies, which we'll show the materials that we use.
It will list all the items that are going to be in a clubhouse.
And then this picture down below here is actually a property that we build.
It was a 2016 application that was awarded in Web City, Missouri.
This is a senior property, but the clubhouse will be very similar.
The left picture is actually a fit in this room, but that's also a storm shelter.
So, as you can tell, it doesn't really look like a storm shelter, unless you know why the walls are so fit.
The next page are the unit plans.
So, as you can see, the one bedroom units are going to be on 7204 square feet.
And then three bedroom units, who are right at, I think it's 1100 living space, but I think it comes
up to about 1,500 with the garage, so 1,500 total.
And those will be more of a black-style, you know, I believe there's a 10-black-cent and 8-black,
so a few 8-black-suits.
So, here's the property map.
You can see here on the left side, that's owned street, because it goes through the north and south.
Our existing property is the Wednesday State.
The parts of the address will be 1,800 redwood-layered, you can see that there's 1,700 redwood-layered,
so what we will extend that red on out eastward, as you can see on the side's land below,
and it will kind of circle around.
Do you have any questions?
I have that too, there's simply-
Can you kind of do the micro-femble?
First of all, I would say, I'm driving, or some, we have all the due places to the south, but they are actually the south.
It might only be concerned, not that they're not quality developers and builders.
I built Rick Schroeder's mother's home when I was building and Kelsey Gorman in Joplin.
They were all in high school, but access would be only on the one street that's there now.
You're going to go down the street and you're going to have one access to Gorman, right?
Can just you look at that.
It's a good talk in the right seat, but you know what I'm just so covered right now with a lot of traffic.
There's people here that live near the film street, and you have 60 more cars, assuming there's two cars per family.
What's there now?
My second-
before units, I know they've got two cars and they, you put that on
Elm Street which, when I developed it, it realized that much traffic would be
there all on one street, maybe it would go once it goes from here to the next
stage and see if it could be. That's the problem I've got, and it's not just mine,
it's anybody that lives out there that's on Elm Street. It's probably my
hand is draining down, working right now. All that water, we have a major issue
right here now, I just talked to the city through, I've been with a mayor, numerous
times, but we were told with it was engineered that that little water there,
actually, that's not, yeah, this is the problem. We're drain here into a drainage ditch
to go back west to the 10 Wednesdays later. That home is water all the time. I've got
pictures over there, colored pictures, and many of my tenants were just
complaining constantly about this heat. I was informed that if we put it in that
way, the city would come in and we saw off them once every two or three years. You kind of
clean that out with a room in the screen for the first two or three times, it was done
water drain perfect. I have a concrete swell, and even today there was water in it,
and we get in there and we shovel out the debris that comes from the street, but drainage
will be a major problem. We know this water comes in here. It will flow into my property, and
then we'll be major issues there, because at the time Biden was engineered, the biggest problem
from the north east corner, the whole 48th or two, well, actually, the 20th, I'll be
a part of this one. There was about a foot drop from that point to the island street to
the opposite corner, and I knew there was a problem then, and when I used to own access to that
property, I had options on it for years, and when Rick and Eric went to purchase it, I just
had a problem with it, because again, they're great, great developers. It's just problem with
access, a water travel, and then the drainage would have to be issued. I don't know how
it's expected to be. You need to hear me in there with you, but you know, you didn't want to have to
be prepared as far as water drain it. And I haven't seen the site in yet, but you're definitely
going to have to do a great something here that I'm interested in.
Remember we've got someone on the phone? Yeah, someone up to the microphone.
And you hear me dead? You can't sleep. Yeah, dead. Yeah, yeah, yeah.
Well, the same was on that south side, out in Gene's north side, there's going to have to be dead.
Water drains west and that whistle that goes under alms tree will definitely have to
Look at that again when that when that
Comes about but I don't know if that's something that
The city would help with or it could be under the
The developers but that's something we want to talk about in the future so we can never help
And address that that are dealing it would be a trade-offs. I think that the the housing
Would be absolutely
An able to use to not only
Great each but
Elstrick needs to be wise when they know that the only
Issues and
I don't know where the money can from but
Right when when when when when when this all comes about and
Permits and there is you don't
Don't be a storm war to be right in
SWP3 plan
Yep, and
We'll be our storm war manager by the ball
And yeah, I just wanted to practice at this point. This is an application so everything is contingent bond
They award from that home housing by agency
We're not requesting building permits at this point. This is just a preliminary claim
We've actually already thought about drainage for this site. It's not actually on this plan
But our account who figures our numbers and and actually comes up with storm water
Numbers he actually doesn't decide he also does services are a laundry
How do you see it?
We've used ancient and interesting engineering in the past. That's I did my and again
So qualified the only problem is when you did your attention on here
Retention wanted to call it. This is still a wetland and it just they were down
Which just falls back into it is never dry and the excuse is we can't moat because it's too wet
Got that from the mayor maybe a week ago and
Kevin and Justin and all that they're involved in it so even tomorrow
We're gonna moat our we don't any moment
But we're gonna moat all this down in here so if you start drying
We won't go any farther, but it's going to be a major issue and
We have water them to us. It would be a lot of legal issues. You know anybody wants to thank
But it's got to be handled the traffic. I can't control
You're through any development
I don't get what it is
That's something that will have to be addressed
And you really can't stop people without it building it's just got to be a range like
Doug said
Wide the streets. You've got all the baby's village. Scott Lane needs to last and in every day. That's the one hell, but
when Scott Lane and Picasso, she'd basically,
that's where it started.
When I bought all that man back in 7879,
who would have thought most of them would be there,
but it is.
I went through the same problem in Kelsey Norman
where Donna Schoer's lives was,
and we had to put 48 inch underground storm range
at every intersection.
Her own employee, the city manager would not let me
even get her meant until that happened.
However, Martin was the engineering firm at the time,
and they said, you've got all this acreage
following you're adding to it.
That was the first build-around there to build,
through that had to put in underground storm range,
and I don't know if they all do it now, should they do.
But drainage will be a problem.
Just to adjust that real quick,
it's not shown on here,
or where that is somewhat of a function,
where a lot of people didn't play it,
if they'll come and say, it's you.
One of the things that we talked about,
is the slope of the lay-in,
folks believe it's eastward,
and like I said, our cost has figured,
if we need to shift this building on the very far east side,
downward, that would still give this plenty of area
and north east corner to put a storm detention area.
The other thing to, that we've factored into this,
because we have experience with this existing property,
is the amount of dirt work that's going to go into this project,
and we're very well in the soil conditions out there,
and we have budgeted in plenty of money for dirt work,
because we have to bring some central amount of dirt into the down,
I believe most of what's out there is a kind of sandy material,
not really great to go on.
So hopefully that will help mitigate some of the drainage concerns
as well.
I've got a couple of questions.
Do you want to, let's close the quote,
have a curing first, if everybody's done,
and then open up their discussion.
Is there anybody else that wants to comment on a couple of here?
OK.
So we'll go ahead and, there's nobody in the other room,
but I'll OK.
So that is the end of public curing.
You can be on board here, OK.
One of my questions is kind of regarding access as well,
as I'm looking at the map of the complex.
One of the things I'm concerned about is how much traffic
will be parked on the street itself,
and the access, that would be a little difficult
for any sort of emergency vehicle, anything like that, weaving down,
because I know some of those other streets, it is already.
And they're not in that, it's not really a circle,
but that type of pattern.
So what is going to be the,
regulations for street parking.
As far as street parking, because these are due places they have garages, that's considered parking spaces.
Right.
So there are also driveways in front of the garages as well.
So most of the garages in the free bedrooms, which are the places in the middle and on the side.
The vehicles will actually be in the driveway.
They won't actually be in the street parking.
The only street parking that you'll see is what is next to the clubhouse community center.
And the one that you're in the apartments that don't.
Because all those other houses down the streets have garages too, and they're still on the street.
Yeah.
So, but the way this pattern is, you have a real hard time getting an emergency vehicle around those cornerash and stuff with thirds.
And the second question is, I hate the term low income housing because it kind of brings up a negative connotation.
But all addresses that I wish they'd say affordable housing.
But, you know, when people in Miami here, low income housing, they think of cars and the yards up on blocks, stuff scattered all over the street, so and so forth.
So what type of, you know, regulation, if you will, as far as the upkeep of the yards and the appearance of that complex is going to be.
Sure.
I would all let our tractor crew speak for itself.
They're not really anything in the regulation pertaining to the upkeep of the property.
We take great credit on what would you, and most of the reason why our properties work the way that they do is because of the management company, you know.
Like I said, they have a great track record.
I agree with you that if I used to determine low income and that's actually a correction that I should have made.
The program is actually called affordable housing and it's been programmed because it has that connotation.
A lot of people in the really think when you think of low income, they think of sectioning housing, which is typically, you know, high-rise building that's got just a low employee units in it.
So yeah, we prefer to call this affordable housing.
So we honestly don't, I'm going to be completely honest, our management company doesn't really take a lot from the tenants.
I mean, we're pretty strict on our rules, and we have a very sensitive lease, and so tenants break our lease, then there's sort of an eviction of this.
And so obviously, you know, we're working.
I speak to our operations director of needs, constantly issuing, I don't want to say evictions, but warning to people for things like, you know, barbecue grows on their balconies and things like that.
So we don't want to have an appearance of working like low income housing.
So, because I'm not familiar with your track record, so I'm just hearing what you're saying, but the last thing my amanese is another complex with junk all over the yards and stuff.
So, I'm trusting this.
That's an important thing to your company and especially the management company is to
You know, because I'm a firm believer that you make something nice and people more apt to keep it nice
If it's junkie, they'll be junkie as well.
Absolutely.
So if it's kind of any, I guess,
We actually, our home office in Dublin is over 20 to 20,
20, 20, 60, and I use 20 of these street.
But we have our properties that surround our office.
There are a couple of conventional properties and then we have a few working
business elements in and around.
And I was going to take you there.
I actually had this very similar situation to happen over in Pittsburgh,
Kansas, probably about six months ago,
who was kind of hesitant on selling his land to us because he had some future plans
for to develop around his property.
And he was worried about the same thing.
And so I invited him over to our one of our website properties.
Which is actually a mix of marked agreements and affordable housing together.
And I said, can you point out to me which one of these units are affordable?
And he said, no, I can't.
They look virtually identical.
The only difference is some finishes on the interiors.
So, you know, he was pleased enough with their parents in the property
that, you know, he went ahead and signed a contract with us.
So, you know, because the property you're boarding is, he does a plan.
And it's one of the more valued, you know, places for people to live as far as, you know,
especially retired people.
And so I would hate something to border that that might, you know, mess that up as well.
So, just throwing those ideas out there in the past.
I can't say I did some research on the property on 20 Springs.
And that's why I went out this morning to take the pictures that I took.
So, I thought I just want to go, because we don't have, we don't have any reported issues.
We don't have any issues that we've been called from tenants.
From tenants, same that the property management is not doing what they should be doing.
We don't have any record of anything like that.
And the reason why I went out there this morning to take pictures was,
I just thought maybe you guys might have a question as to what the current property looked like.
And I did see what you're mentioning, and I was going to visit with Kevin about the storm drainage there,
needs to be cleaned out.
You wouldn't be able to do that.
What Tim and Mitchen, we spent about 28,000 dollars just in Vincent, because I was losing tenants, children.
And he said to do a little walk-and-back from the existing property throughout property.
And in some cases, picking up little yard sconces and moving them next door.
People would come out, where's it at, you know.
And we went ahead and spent money from Chris Lane all the way around and completely.
boarded it up to the trees. I'm just concerned, will there be any perimeter, screening,
as to kind of make it more of a gain of community? Wouldn't it just be all open?
Because you will get a lot of water from a good there, not with a good thing to stop that.
Right, right.
I would, I don't want to tell you wrong yet. So typically we do build sentences around our heart,
because most of the handling of these single-family developments, obviously, those usually end up being
for cell homes after they come out of the program. So we usually don't build sentences around this,
but I would have to double-check on the cost as far as I've been.
Yeah, I had to do it, which, like, he said, one way you did it.
And we have a lot of original tenants. It's been there 15 years.
That, like, stay in, as long as I've given them that access and crystalline,
and not much water coming off of me.
I could say before, the quality of this construction, the produce, or even more,
rather than the other hand, something's controlled, which just landed you have to use it.
But drainage, traffic, if you consider six to the cars, and that much more with all the company they have.
And affordable housing tends to bring other people there to visit for that many more cars.
And the streets will be, will be full, whether it's for the emergency, is it a lot?
I see it on M. L. Street, a little name that I built, virtually not built.
The way you post it together is a high-insight meal now. I couldn't stop it now, but as I was building them,
I made a lot larger and more space.
It's a place, a young street was just caught.
I've taken the blame, it wasn't done, right?
I'll just make sure that I understand that.
And I'll talk to some, from Mr. Scherter, letting me know your concerns.
But you're saying you're having the same issues as far as the street parking,
and that's also your concern about the emergency vehicles.
Are you having those same existing problems on Ryan?
I don't pay as many people.
I didn't pay too much. I'm nine years old.
But it's company that gets there. I've never had an issue with all three parking,
because I'm 100 foot on each new place.
So if I don't want to be able to provide a single quarter of the budget, it sets back.
And the overall size of the law is an average of 100, 130, 150.
So space wasn't my issue, it was just, we know if it can.
We'll start in the update in final plans.
We can improve the dimensions of the driveway.
And if we need to, we'll apply a green space to where we need to reconfigure.
Okay, do you have any other questions?
Do you have any questions?
I don't think so.
Sorry, I'm good.
No, I'm good.
The issue of traffic, we talk about, you know, it's a problem.
I don't know how it's going to be resolved.
Well, I don't know.
Why, I don't know.
Through those.
Many cities would be like, you know,
there's much of somebody sitting there because the traffic is stopped.
They'd just say, no, it's agricultural or you can build single family homes because
you know, you're going to have bird and half-acre pots, not, you know, on 20,
so many acres, I've put 46 lots.
In the name of the experience, why?
It's got ladies and all of them.
So, I mean, what do you do?
You've got to do well in numbers and they've got to make the work,
you know.
So, if you crank them together and that's just the way they work.
The money is when they start doing it.
We all do.
Play a little bit of your nation.
And there's no other way to get back there because there are tracks on the east side.
You'd have to go through on the J&M, probably.
I'm straight all the way back.
I tried to buy my niece and I thought the viewers would go,
I still can't even walk through.
To make it that a picture.
But I stepped out and we were going to go in the skyline.
It's just that it did do three.
It stepped out.
It didn't happen.
So, unfortunately, I don't have any information.
As far as the traffic.
But we were agreeing to extend the road.
You know, to the property of that.
You know, we're wildly.
A lot of times they do traffic camps.
But there's no.
Well, I mean, you know, at one point, maybe you consider putting a stop sign on
and such because they're getting pretty fast.
I just live one block off the element.
The stop signs out.
I'm on the side street through right now.
I'm talking stop.
Go for it.
We only got the four-way stop there and the one that is parked.
You know, because they do go pretty fast.
You got to have a pedal.
Yes.
Slow times.
So slow tires on me.
Okay.
Do we have any other questions?
Thank you very much.
All right.
Number seven is enjoy.
Oh, excuse me.
That's all I'm sorry.
Got it.
Those two make the regulations in.
Okay.
We need a recommendation.
I was to go ahead and approve.
through our recommendation to change this agricultural to multi-thing so well-except.
So you're actually asking for a vote to recommend to the Council, the annexation and
zoning of this property as residential multi-family.
Contend it on, you know, getting funding from the state.
If they don't get the funding from the state, then it just stays agriculture and it's not
an extensive city.
And there will be any traffic studies or any issues or resolved on traffic.
No, it's right.
So yes, it comes later.
So right now, they don't have all that vote right now.
They have to have an annexed and zone residential multi-family before the 25th of June
so that they can submit their application for the tax credits.
So that's the sense.
Okay, so if we resout it, annex it in their project, it doesn't materialize for whatever
reason doesn't go back to agriculture.
Yes.
It doesn't change from what it is today, it's not annexed and it's agriculture in the county.
And then who would, who would the responsible party be to handle the issue of traffic on Elchery, who
would address that?
What are we going to end that white point?
We could ask on the side, we could ask the street department about the traffic count there
and that would be a whole different issue.
Oh, we're going to need for the approval of zoning and annexation and if they don't approve
the exit.
So when you annex in a piece of property into the city, you also have to sign a zoning
to it.
Normally, the zoning is a residential single family zone, but when you annex it in, you want
to get it zone for the purpose in which you're going to use the property of right.
Oh, make a motion in the green, send that forward.
We have a motion that we have a second.
Is that you, you're going to get a 10, I'm sorry, I'm going to go, all right, right now.
Hi.
Western, all right, camera, all right.
Okay, I need a motion to adjourn.
Good.
Second one.
Aye.
Riddles.
What?
Cumbrow.
Aye.
Weston.
In-prem.
Aye.
All right.
Good morning.
We have a check sheet for you.
Sure.
Our mind.
I've got a change closed real quick.
I've got your devour.
In-prem.
Drums.
Peace.
On the right.
Yeah.
On the left.
On the right.
The right.
and I'm only sucker that's filling up the go and cut it right here.